Namo Buddha Shakyamuni.
Nam Mô Phật Bổn Sư Thích Ca Mâu Ni Kính
Greetings, dear fellow practitioners! The
chào quý đạo hữu thế là chúng ta cũng đã
Buddha's Birthday is approaching. How
sắp đến mùa Phật Đản rồi cứ bảo làm sao
fleeting and impermanent our lives are! It seems like
mà cuộc đời chúng ta nó nhanh vô thường
only yesterday we were young and beautiful, and
thế mới hôm nào mà nă thanh nữ tú xong
today our faces are already as plump as
Hôm nay nhìn đến cái gương mặt đã sánh
Chinese apples. Dear fellow practitioners, another life spent
ngang quả táo Tàu rồi có Quý đạu Hữu
clinging to youth,
thêm một cuộc đời cứ lanh quanh đi níu
but we can't hold on
kéo tuổi xuân mãi Chả níu kéo được bởi
because a year passes so quickly. Buddha's Birthday is over, and
vì một năm nó nhanh thế mới Phật Đản
today it's already Buddha's Birthday again! So,
xong Hôm nay cũng đã lại Phật Đản rồi
considering
Thế thì mới tính ra là ở trên cái quả
how many eons it takes for a Buddha to be born on this earth, and yet he only lived in this world
địa cầu này vô lượng kiếp bao nhiêu kiếp
preaching the Dharma for 49 years—isn't that
trụ thế sa Bà thuyết pháp có 49 năm có
short, dear fellow practitioners? It's incredibly short! How difficult it is for
ngắn không các quý đạo hữu quá ngắn làm
us Buddhists to cultivate ourselves to be
sao mà những người phật tử chúng ta tu
present at the time of the
cái gì mà để được chúng ta có mặt ở lúc
Buddha's birth. Even now,
Đức Phật ra đời khó vô cùng cho đến bây
we are born in
giờ đấy mà chúng ta sinh ra trong thời
this era of the Dharma, and encountering the true Dharma is
mặt pháp này mà gặp được chánh pháp cũng
incredibly difficult, isn't it, dear
vô cùng khó khăn có phải không quý đạo
practitioners? Even when we encounter it, developing the intention to practice is difficult; developing the intention to practice is
hữu gặp được rồi mà phát cái tâm tu cũng
even more difficult when the circumstances around us allow us to practice.
cảnh bên cạnh cho mình tu lại càng khó
Furthermore, isn't it incredibly difficult to find a worthy Dharma friend?
nữa có phải có quý Đạ Hữu khó vô cùng
Time flies so fast.
đấy thời gian thì trôi nhanh như vậy đấy
However, such auspicious opportunities are so
Thế Như nhưng mà cái duyên tốt đẹp thì
rare, so small, so short. So,
ít quá là bé quá là ngắn cho nên là cứ
looking at this time, we
nhìn vào thời gian thế này thì chúng ta
must strive hard. If we lose this lifetime, we
phải cố gắng thôi nhá mất một kiếp sống
don't know when we
này rồi thì lại không biết đến bao giờ
will encounter the true Dharma again. If we lose this lifetime, perhaps we will only find the true Dharma
mới gặp được chánh pháp nữa mất kiếp này
when Maitreya Buddha is born, or perhaps we
rồi thì có khi đến khi Đức Phật Di Lặc
will be born again. The Dharma-ending age of
khi lại sinh vậy Thời Mạt Pháp của đức
Maitreya Buddha is also uncertain;
Phật Di đặc nữa th không biết là đến bao
it's vast and boundless. Sometimes we
giờ nó mênh mông lắm đôi khi chúng ta
just keep weighing our
chỉ có loanh quanh cân đo
desires in this life: "I really need to get
giữa dục ở đời nào tôi rất cần phải đi
married, I need to have children." We weigh things like that for countless lifetimes, haven't we, dear Dharma friends? We
lấy vợ lấy chồng tôi cần có con cứ cân
weigh things like that for countless lifetimes. And
đo kiểu đấy vô lượng kiếp cũng cân đo
even now, we continue to weigh things. If we don't give up on that scale, we
cũng cân đo rồi Thế đến bây giờ vẫn tiếp
have to weigh things in every lifetime, but we
đấy thì kiếp nào cũng phải cân nhưng cân
never get tired of weighing them. Therefore, the
đi cân lại vẫn không chán cho nên Đức
Buddha's birth is a very rare opportunity, so let's cultivate a mindful and contemplative mind.
Phật ra đời rất là h hữu duyên cho nên
Hopefully, we will welcome the
tâm chế quán mong rằng là chúng ta đón
Buddha's Birthday with a truly enlightened mind,
mùa Phật Đản với cái Tâm thật là giác
concerned for ourselves.  My esteemed friends, you must
ngộ lo lắng cho mình các quý Đạ Hữu phải
worry about yourselves; no one else can worry
lo lắng cho mình thôi không ai lo lắng
for you anymore. In this life,
hộ cho mình được nữa cuộc đời này cứ
we are just busy measuring and
chúng ta chỉ có lanh quanh cân đo đong
weighing money and rice, feeding
đếm đồng tiền bắt gạo Nuôi cái thân vô
this impermanent body. This body does
thường này thôi cái thân này nó chả nó
n't listen to us at all. If we tell it not to
chẳng nghe mình tí nào C bảo nó không
age, it won't listen; if we tell it not to get
già nó không chịu nghe mình bảo nó không
sick, it won't listen. It goes its own way;
bệnh nó cũng chẳng nghe mình nó tự đường
it gets old when it gets old, it gets sick when it gets
nó nó đi nó già là nó già nó bệnh là nó
sick, it chooses to roll over and die whenever it wants. It doesn't
bệnh nó thích lăn quay ra chết nào nó
listen to us at all, does it, my
lăn quay ra nó có nghe mình cái gì đâu
esteemed friends? But
có phải không quý Đại Hữu thế nhưng mà
we calculate too much for it,
chúng ta thì tính toán cho nó quá nhiều
using our whole lives and energy to
dùng cả cuộc đời sức lực của mình tính
calculate its gains and losses, right and wrong, fighting and
toán cho nó hơn thua phải trái tranh đấu
calculating everything for it. And yet, in
đủ thứ tính toán cho nó
the end,
thế mà cuối
it's gone. That means the heart is too sincere.
cùng nó ra đi Tức là ở đây tâm chân quá
For example, two friends,
nói ví dụ Hai thằng hai thằng bạn với
one a close friend, the other a close friend. They
nhau một thằng là bạn là thân một thằng
play together, but they're very fickle. The close
bạn là tâm hai thằng chơi với nhau nhưng
friend gets
dở mặt lắm coi như là cái thằng thân nó
offended and leaves without regret,
tự ái cái là nó ra đi không thương tiếc
while the close friend is filled with
trong lúc cái thằng tâm thì đang gì đang
regret. The close friend
rất là nuối tiếc đấy Cái thằng tâm thì
keeps telling the close friend, "Just take it easy, you'll get old soon."
cứ bảo cái thằng thân là thôi mày từ từ
I'm enjoying my youth a bit, and my
mày hắng già để tao hưởng tí tuổi trẻ
friend says, "Just leave me alone, mind your own
thằng thân nó bảo mày kệ đời mày việc
business, mind my own business, is
mày việc mày việc tao việc tao có phải
n't that right?" That guy, Tâm, is
không Cái thằng cái thằng Tâm lúc nào
always dragging my friend along. "Oh my god,
cũng đi kéo cái thằng thân Ôi giời ơi
this place is wrinkled, this place is like this and that!"
cái chỗ này nhăn rồi cái chỗ này thế này
My friend replies, "The
thế kia rồi Thằng thân nó trả lời chứ
more you lose sleep, the
mày mà càng mất ngủ Mày no cho tao ấy
more you worry about me, the more I'll turn against you. The more you worry about me, the
thì tao càng giở mặt với mày mày Càng lo
older I get. I don't care about you. You need to have esteemed fellow
cho tao thì tao càng già thế Tao mặc kệ
practitioners. I don't care about you.
mày C phải có quý đạo hữu Tao mặc kệ mày
How do you want to worry? You worry about these two guys.
Mày muốn lo kiểu gì Mày lo hai thằng này
They've never been friends. Only
nó chưa bao giờ làm bạn với nhau chỉ có
when we have the
khi nào mà chúng ta chúng ta được ở cái
opportunity to become monks and cultivate mindfulness will these two
duyên xuất gia tu đạo thân tâm chánh
be friends. But
niệm thì hai thằng này nó mới là bạn Còn
when we are greedy, these two
khi chúng ta tham dục thì hai thằng này
are never friends, esteemed fellow practitioners.
chưa bao giờ là bạn các quý Đạ Hữu hai
These two fight each other terribly.
thằng này đấu đá nhau khiếp khủng luôn
For example, when we go to apply for jobs, and
Ví dụ Chúng ta đi xin công ăn việc làm
this job requires a
với cái việc này nó cần phải có cái hình
good appearance, this guy says, "I don't care about you,
tướng tốt đẹp thì thằng này nó mà kệ mày
that's your business." Even though you go to work
đấy là việc của mày Tuy rằng mày đi làm
and earn money for me to eat,
mày kiếm tiền cho tao ăn ấy nhưng việc
my getting old is my business,
tao già là việc của tao việc tao bị làm
what happens to me is my business, I don't care about you.  Is
sao là việc của tao mà kệ mày có phải
n't that right, dear friends? Sometimes we
không quý Đại Hữu nhiều lúc chúng ta
have to use our
cũng phải dùng cái trí quán chúng ta tư
intellect to think and realize that
duy để chúng ta thấy là đúng là cái
this mind is serving the
thằng Tâm này nó đi nó phục vụ cái thằng
body, which is so unfair and ungrateful. Isn't that right,
thân nó bất công lắm nó bạc bẽo lắm Có
dear friends? Let the
phải không quý Đại Hữu Thôi thì để cái
mind take care of itself; it will find
thằng Tâm lo cho cái thằng Tâm đi nó còn
liberation. But worrying about
giải thoát chứ còn cứ lo cho cái thằng
this body is too much trouble and brings no benefit, isn't
thân này nhọc quá không được cái lợi ích
it? Waiting for you to go to work is
gì có đúng không quý đợi Hữu đi làm mà
exhausting. Feeding it from
Mệt ơi là mệt cho nó ăn ăn xong từ trưa
noon until evening, it's already complaining, it's
ăn xong đến chiều nó đã kêu đ rồi không
impossible to keep up with serving you. You're the one who's always complaining, are
thể nào làm mà phục vụ kịp Mày cơ có
n't you? Then there's no money.
phải không Thế rồi Tiền thì không có mày
You see something, your tongue gets all excited, you ca
nhìn thấy cái gì lưỡi mày cái thằng Lưỡi
n't stand it, and you keep
cũng thèm thèm không chịu được lại đi
urging the mind. It's so miserable, is
giục cái thằng Tâm nó rất là khốn khổ
n't it? So sometimes, when we're feeling a little
phải không Nên nhiều lúc chúng ta mà vui
cheerful, let's watch the play
vui tí chúng ta xem cái vở kịch của hai
these two are acting out together, okay? To
cái thằng này nó đóng với nhau nhá Để
make life more lively,
cho cho cuộc đời nó thêm sinh động các
dear friends.
quý Đại Hữu ạ
[music]
[âm nhạc]